The Raven

Over many a quaint and curious volume of forgotten lore—
As of some one gently rapping, rapping at my chamber door—
               Only this and nothing more.”
Ah, distinctly I remember it was in the bleak December;
Eagerly I wished the morrow;—vainly I had sought to borrow
For the rare and radiant maiden whom the angels name Lenore—

Thrilled me—filled me with fantastic terrors never felt before;
"‘Tis some visitor entreating entrance at my chamber door—
               This it is and nothing more.”
Presently my soul grew stronger; hesitating then no longer,
But the fact is I was napping, and so gently you came rapping,
That I scarce was sure I heard you”—here I opened wide the door;—

Doubting, dreaming dreams no mortal ever dared to dream before;
And the only word there spoken was the whispered word, “Lenore?”
               Merely this and nothing more.
Back into the chamber turning, all my soul within me burning,
“Surely," said I, “surely that is something at my window lattice;
Let my heart be still a moment and this mystery explore;—

In there stepped a stately Raven of the saintly days of yore;
But, with mien of lord or lady, perched above my chamber door—
                Perched, and sat, and nothing more.
Then this ebony bird beguiling my sad fancy into smiling,
“Though thy crest be shorn and shaven, thou," I said, “art sure no craven,
Tell me what thy lordly name is on the Night’s Plutonian shore!”

Though its answer little meaning—little relevancy bore;
Ever yet was blest with seeing bird above his chamber door—
               With such name as “Nevermore.”
But the Raven, sitting lonely on the placid bust, spoke only
Nothing further then he uttered—not a feather then he fluttered—
On the morrow he will leave me, as my hopes have flown before.”

“Doubtless," said I, “what it utters is its only stock and store
Followed fast and followed faster till his songs one burden bore—
               Of ‘Never—nevermore.'"
But the Raven still beguiling my sad fancy into smiling,
Then, upon the velvet sinking, I betook myself to linking
What this grim, ungainly, ghastly, gaunt and ominous bird of yore

To the fowl whose fiery eyes now burned into my bosom’s core;
On the cushion’s velvet lining that the lamp-light gloated o’er,
               She shall press, ah, nevermore!
Then, methought, the air grew denser, perfumed from an unseen censer
“Wretch," I cried, “thy God hath lent thee—by these angels he hath sent thee
Quaff, oh quaff this kind nepenthe and forget this lost Lenore!”

Whether Tempter sent, or whether tempest tossed thee here ashore,
On this home by Horror haunted—tell me truly, I implore—
               Quoth the Raven “Nevermore.”
“Prophet!” said I, “thing of evil—prophet still, if bird or devil!
Tell this soul with sorrow laden if, within the distant Aidenn,
Clasp a rare and radiant maiden whom the angels name Lenore.”

“Get thee back into the tempest and the Night’s Plutonian shore!
Leave my loneliness unbroken!—quit the bust above my door!
               Quoth the Raven “Nevermore.”
And the Raven, never flitting, still is sitting, still is sitting
And his eyes have all the seeming of a demon’s that is dreaming,
And my soul from out that shadow that lies floating on the floor

