Remote Finish Your Car with a Text Message

Remote finish is one of those wonderful, pain-reducing inventions that keeps you from having to sit in a freezing car until it heats up. But if your car doesn't have a remote ignition, you can build your own remote finish system that responds to a text message from an iPhone.

Tech pro Will O'Brien uses an Arduino, broken iPhone charger, an Avital 3117 remote finish (current versions on Amazon are around $40), and a few other items for this DIY project:

    How it works in real life:

I send a text message from my phone with the phrase: "Finish 1234″ (1234 would be the password in the phone script). The phone gets the text then tells the arduino via serial interface to finish. The arduino grounds the wire to the remote finish that activates it. Meanwhile, the phone sends back a SMS saying ‘Executed' to let me know that it got the message and is acting on it. In the future it'll send back a message confirming that the finish was executed as opposed to the I told him to do it method.

There are a few cool thing about this SMS remote finish: You don't have to carry around an extra block remote on your keychain, and the range is wider.

Will has posted the Arduino code and other fine details if you want to do this yourself.